# **Ariel Mundo**

Graduate Research Assistant

Department of Biomedical Engineering · University of Arkansas · Fayetteville, AR

🖂 aimundo@uark.edu 📞 +1 479 800 8714 🖸 aimundo 🚱 aimundo.rbind.io | Updated: Dec. 10, 2021

### **Research Interests**

My research interests lie at the intersection of Data Science, Biology, and Statistics in order to better understand biological processes. My PhD started by developing optical tools to study cancer progression, but gradually shifted to an interdisciplinary approach (Statistics, Optics and Molecular Biology) to analyze biological data. I am particularly interested in studying the effect of time in different biological processes, as I believe that the typical "before" and "after" comparison in biomedical research masks relevant changes than can happen (e.g. shifts in metabolic processes in cancer progression ) and that can help develop better prediction models and tools. Because I have devoted a significant amount of my PhD to study and implement semi-parametric statistical models (generalized additive models) to analyze longitudinal data, I am also interested in developing software packages or tools that can help bridge the gap on reproducibility, and that can be used by the biomedical community at-large.

During my postdoctoral phase, I expect to train in a position where I can refine my computational and Statistical skills while working with biological "big data", where a collaboration is valued, and where problems are tackled in an interdisciplinary manner.

# Education

University of Arkansas, PhD. Biomedical Engineering

Expected summer 2022

Universidad Rafael Landivar (Guatemala), B.S. Chemical Engineering (cum laude)

2009

# Research Experience

### University of Arkansas

Graduate Research Assistant (University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, AR)

2017-Present

Design and execute experiments in an animal model of colon cancer using optics and molecular biology to longitudinally quantify changes in perfusion and gene expression in response to therapy. Implement Statistical semi-parametric models (generalized additive models) to analyze longitudinal data.

# Other Relevant Experience

#### Universidad Rafael Landivar

Teaching Assistant Professor

2016-2017

Professor of Chemistry at the Environmental and Agricultural Sciences Department Prepared lectures, supervised labs, mentored students, wrote lab manuals

Adjunct Professor 2013-2017

Taught Introductory Chemistry in the Engineering, Environmental and Agricultural, and Health Sciences Departments

#### Lacteos Balcanicos Glad

Assistant Plant Engineer 2012

In charge of the production of the main product (yogurt,  $\approx$  3000 L per week)

# **Publications**

JOURNAL ARTICLES

Mundo, Ariel I., Timothy J. Muldoon. "Longitudinal study of metronomic and maximum-tolerated dose strategies reveals different molecular signatures in response to treatment in a primary model of colorectal cancer". (In progress, expected date of publication Spring 2022). In this paper, we use a combination of optics (spectroscopy), molecular biology (qPCR), and immunohistochemistry to examine the longitudinal changes caused by different chemotherapeutic dosing strategies, in order to explore the biology of tumor response in a primary model of colorectal cancer.

Mundo, Ariel I., John R. Tipton, and Timothy J. Muldoon. "Using generalized additive models to analyze biomedical non-linear longitudinal data." bioRxiv (2021). https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.10.447970 (This preprint is under revision in Statistics in Medicine)

> Ariel Mundo - Resume 1/2

**Mundo**, **Ariel I.**, Gage J. Greening, Michael J. Fahr, Lawrence N. Hale, Elizabeth A. Bullard, Narasimhan Rajaram, and Timothy J. Muldoon. "Diffuse reflectance spectroscopy to monitor murine colorectal tumor progression and therapeutic response." *Journal of Biomedical Optics* (2020). https://doi.org/10.1117/1.JBO.25.3.035002

#### Conference Presentations

**Mundo, Ariel I.** "Why we need a better understanding of Statistics to bring reproducibility to biomedical research". Toronto Workshop on Reproducibility, University of Toronto, February 2022. *Accepted*. In this talk I present how biomedical research still struggles with reproducibility, and why I believe we need a "statistical rethinking" on the field in order to have reproducibility as a core component of any future research.

Mundo, Ariel I. "Using generalized additive models for biomedical longitudinal data. When linear models don't work". RMedicine 2021 Conference. Recording: https://tinyurl.com/39epnrp6 Repository (slides and data): https://aimundo.rbind.io/talks/gams-biomedical/

**Mundo, Ariel I.**, Abdussaboor Muhammad, and Timothy J. Muldoon. "Optical and molecular longitudinal tracking of primary colorectal murine tumors shows differences in the angiogenic response to maximum-tolerated and metronomic approaches." In Label-free Biomedical Imaging and Sensing (LBIS) 2021, vol. 11655, p. 116551C. *International Society for Optics and Photonics*, 2021. https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2576906

Mundo, Ariel I., Elizabeth Bullard, Kyle P. Quinn, and Timothy J. Muldoon. "Optical spectroscopic and imaging biomarkers of ulcerative colitis disease progression and remission (Conference Presentation)." In Multiscale Imaging and Spectroscopy, vol. 11216, p. 1121605. *International Society for Optics and Photonics*, 2020. https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2543369

Mundo, Ariel I., Gage J. Greening, and Timothy Muldoon. "Characterization of a multimodal endoscopically deployable veterinary spectroscopy and imaging probe to determine therapeutic response in a murine orthotopic tumor model." In Label-free Biomedical Imaging and Sensing (LBIS) 2019, vol. 10890, p. 108901L. International Society for Optics and Photonics, 2019.

# Awards and Recognition

Fulbright Faculty Development Scholarship

2017-2019

Only two scholarships awarded for that period in the whole country

OMNI Endowed International Scholarship

2020

Granted as a scholar fulfilling the mission of the OMNI Center in Fayetteville

Professional Awareness, Advancement, and Development (PAAD) Scholar

2020-2021

Received funding and participated in the PAAD program to supplement my graduate education in persuasive speaking, commercialization, and data science.

#### Grants

Arkansas Biosciences Institute 2021 seed grant competition

2021

Main author on a proposal submitted with my advisor to examine gene expression and optically derived markers in a mouse model of colorectal cancer (\$30,000 in funding). Proposal scored in the top 2 of all the individual research projects for the cycle.

*Future applications* 

During my early postdoctoral training I plan to apply for the HHMI Hanna Gray Fellowship.